Hello, everyone.
Welcome back.
In this lesson, we are going to see how to use multiple ADC channels with a DMA.
So I'm going to create a new project or come over here, file new project.
This time we are going to use P, a one, MP or two.
So I just said I must ADC Pier one.
I said this to ADC in one piece to our side as to ADC into.
And also, I should mention, it's not compulsory to always setup the system core that we always do.
We can leave it.
You only have to set us up if you are, you want to set all on use.
PS as input to PS.
So there is an option.
I'll show you when we click code generator over here, OK?
And we come to, um, we come to advance setters.
Um, we come to code generator.
We come to this tub over here and a code generator.
This is set all free pins as analog pins.
I should say.
So when we set off free pins, us analog pins, it helps save power.
The reason why we, uh, we always configure the RCC and then the system over here is so that those
pins don't get set as analog pins.
So if you want to use set pins as analog pins.
So set on on use pins as analog pins.
Then you always have to set your racc.
And this is this.
This options here.
You always have to set them accordingly so that the pins will be set by if you don't want to use it,
you can leave it to its default state.
Okay.
So I'm just gonna show you the example where we don't set this.
We just leave it and proceed.
Um, so we've set in a and in one and in two so we can come over here.
Clock configuration.
Too often we just keep the clock.
We don't interact with a timer much.
Okay.
This time I'm going to change the clock to ninety six megahertz.
I'll just type 96 over here and then I'll hit enter.
Everything else is going to be adjusted.
Click okay.
Over here.
So it's going to adjust the various parts of the system to enable my HSC.
Okay.
To be 96, just like I've typed.
All right.
So this is where we have changed this to HCO, key of change, the Ishioka 296.
And he says the maximum you can get to is 100 may go ahead.
OK.
So now let's go and configure our ADC channels.
I'm going to come back to the Pinart and Configuration and then select system view and then, oh, click
on ADC.
And it's opened, but I've gotta expand it from here.
So click here to expand it.
We use in in one and in two.
That is why they are ticked.
I'm going to come under parameter settings and I'm going to set the.
It is a clock to lessie.
We can divide by eight is fine.
And we can leave the, um, the resolution the same, so we said in this project, we are going to use
the DMA.
So we have to enable that.
Also, we want continuous mode.
So I'm going to enable continuous mode over here.
And DMA continuous request.
I'm going to enable that as well.
Well, we have to do is actually enables scan mode or enables con mode over here.
So what we need to do is and neighbors can mode.
We don't need to enable continuous conversion mode.
So just scan mode enabled.
And then we have to enable DME.
But when you click this dropdown, you don't see the enable option because they expect us to select
the DME first in the version four of Cuba makes.
You could have just selected by inversion five.
You first have to come to DMA settings.
And then you add the DMA.
So you click on ADD and then select over here.
I'm gonna say ADC one now that I've added it.
I can come back to the parameter settings.
And then when I click this, a dropdown does says enable dia DME continuous request and enabled.
Right.
So because we have two conversions, we can set two channels.
We can set a number of conversions to two.
Okay.
So now we have two conversions, the two conversions.
Therefore we have two ranked.
We have run quanti rank two.
So we've got to select the ranks.
We've got to set up the ranks.
So rank basically means which one shall be, um.
Which one should be sampled first?
Is it channel number one or channel number two.
Currently says rank number one is channel number one.
We can leave this rank.
Number two is still channel number one.
So I'm gonna change this to channel number two.
So rank number one is channel number one.
Ranked number two is channel.
Number two, if you have sixteen channels, you'd have 16 ranks and you can arrange them in that order.
The sampling time I'm gonna select for 80 over here and then for 80.
Over here as well.
So once we've done this, we can go back to the DME tub.
We've already added a DME demoed.
We wanted to be secular so they would go back to the top or select Sechler over here and then over here,
data with.
I'm just gonna select a word size, meaning 32 bit.
Okay.
And then this is all we have to do.
And if we want to change the priority, we can change from here.
But we can leave it for this lesson.
So now I can go to the, um, the generate code or click over here.
And then I'll give the project a name.
Call it ADC Unescorted DME.
Multichannel DME.
OK.
And then also like to my two chain.
Then a creek generates like this.
I'll open the project.
So there's the project.
It's opened.
I'm going to clean up a bit.
So in the Cuban mic setup, we initialize to ADC pins, P1 and P2.
So we have two channels, meaning we can connect to send source to a white board and record the ADC.
So to use this and the DME, we can just order result in an array.
I'm going to declare a global array over here.
I'll see you into to underscore team because we declared our DMA a data size to be Web site.
What basically means that two bits of data size.
And I'm gonna call the central values.
And because we have two Chernow's, I'll pass two over here like this.
So what we have to do is now start the ABC with the DMA.
We seen how to just study ABC.
Hi, ladies.
You start.
We've seen how to study a D.C. would interrupt how ADT ADC starts on the score, I.T..
Now, we're gonna start with DMA and we can go to our ADC module to see the function before I write
it.
So I'll come to dry this or come to haul driver source and then I'll double click on ADC.
Don't see over here like this and then I'm gonna search control F over here and then I'm gonna search
ADC on this call.
Start on the score DME and then hit enter.
Okay.
So that's the function.
That's the function.
It says and navel adc DMA request after last transfer and enables ADC paired for each ADC uh and and
enables ADC peripheral.
Okay.
This first line, the second line H ADC pointer basically talks about the argument.
The first argument is the arm is the pointer to the ADC Hando.
And then the second one is the data.
We jumped.
Let's see.
OK.
The second one here, the second parameter.
What does it say?
The second parameter is the data destination buffer, which is what we've declared a global variable
we've declared.
And the third one is the length of the data to be transferred from ATC peripheral to memory.
Okay.
So that's the function we require.
I'm gonna copy this and then I'm gonna paste it in in here.
So we don't need a return.
And I'm gonna pull comment here.
One start.
One here starts in D.C. with DME.
Function.
Okay.
So the first one is, so what, ADC Hondo?
The second one is the data buffer, as I point out to you, instead, to underscore T..
So I'm gonna bring our buffer over here.
And the second one is the length.
The length is just too.
Gonna pass this amber over here like this.
So in this experiment, you can guess I've got a sense or a potential meta connected to P a one and
another one connected to P E two.
And what we're gonna do is add a wah sense of values, um, array here to our live expressions, window
into debug view.
And then we're going to turn the knobs and see if indeed we can get the analog reading.
So I'm gonna click over here to build and it's built in now.
Okay.
The reason we have the theory is we don't need to put ampersand here.
It's expected you in thirty two or three.
Okay.
Now let's build.
Right.
The ABC.
ABC.
The ABC on the list.
It's ABC one.
No, simply age.
ABC can show over here.
It's ABC one.
Click here to build.
OK.
Now we have no error, no warning.
So before we go, actually let's see the code generated.
Course you can see each ADC and HDMI, HTC One over here.
And indeed, we can see that there is extra code generated in our ADC.
This is our ADC in its function.
This is the standard in it.
We go with our ADC.
Now, if you see we have Ronke one over here, which is for ADC Channel one, run two, which is for
ADC Channel two.
And there is another function here which initializes the DME.
And over here it sets the DMA priority as well as enables the interruptive for the DME.
This other function DME in its function.
Right.
So we can go to the debug for and see, you know.
I'm gonna click here to go to the debugger.
DoubleClick this.
I say, okay, over here.
Let's call it a success for me.
Um, let's see.
Let's go to our live expressions.
We can take this out.
This is from a previous project.
You can just right click and remove or.
And I'm going to add this new one called Sense of values, plural.
Okay, so because it's an way we can expand here to see the first and the second.
OK.
So I'm want to click here to run.
Now, as you can see, we have our ADC one value here.
We have the, um.
The one connected to appear to this is Channel two.
Channel two is reading three thousand to five one.
I'm going to turn the nub of Channel Zero, which is, uh, the knob of Channel One, which is ADC Index
zero.
Remember, index your index one.
And then we have Channel one, Channel two.
So index series for Channel one.
Index one is which I know two.
So I'm gonna turn the potential meter for this index.
One.
Senseor.
Let's see.
Okay, let's not change it.
I'll take a look at it right my way, I wasn't connected properly.
Okay, so now the second one is moved to the position of ground.
The second potential meter, which is connected to Channel two, is tend to the wire to the direction
of the wire that connects to ground.
So we see that it's read in this, whereas the other one is tend towards fee plus plus.
Now I'm going to turn the other one.
I'm going to turn this one to the position to always be a plus plus mine and I'm going to move it to
the opposite direction.
Remember, it's a potential meter with three legs.
Right.
And as you can see, they both have higher values.
Now, of course, they've both moved towards, you know, the, um, the DVD, uh, the five foot order,
three, four, two line, basically.
Basically, there's a sign.
So it's just like the other ADC experiment that we did, um, just turn into a potential meter in opposite
directions and based on the direction the analog value is low or high.
So this shows how to have multiple channels which ADC.
So you can use this for ten channels if you want.
If you had 10 channels, then the buffer size, you would be ten.
And then you would have an array of 10 element.
And each one will belong to each channel.
And you can you can, um, you can take it from the array and process it accordingly, such that if
I want to channel one, I can just see, I can just see each one equals sense of values.
Array
Index zero.
And I know this will be giving me my ADC Channel one value and I can take this and put it in the DSP
algorithm or whatever.
I'll go with them.
I hope for further process.
And if I want to Channel two, I know Channel two is looking at the index one so I can just see Channel
two you cross.
I can just say Channel two because this.
I can just see, um, Johno, to of.
Index one.
Actually, I'll show you how this is, because I don't want to leave it stored in the array like that.
Okay.
So it's not over yet.
I'm going to exit this now.
I'm going to come here and then I'm gonna cut this.
And this is the.
Often when we use in DME, the beauty is that we don't have to be read in anything from the we don't
have to be rude in anything from the wild.
Want to say we want to, you know, take this and put it in some, uh, some local variables or whatever.
This is Channel one.
Channel two.
I'm going to declare two local variables here.
I'll say this, as for a little, by the way, it's good to set these things, Swiller, too.
And then I'll come over here and then I'll declare local to local verbose.
That's local because I'm declaring that within the main function, what is outside the main function
is global.
OK.
For those of you who are not aware you into 32 on a score.
T, c, h one.
C, it's two.
So we have two local variables over here.
And we say in C, each one equals sense of the index.
You see H two core sense of value index one.
Okay, so we'll click over here to build.
It's appealed successfully.
What do we have here?
Okay.
So, okay.
The function doesn't accept role at all.
Of course not.
Okay.
We check this out.
So our warning is saved.
No more warning.
What does this one see you in thirty to where it was.
Each one said, but not used.
See, each one is used here.
How come we cannot see it?
See each one.
Okay, let's build again and see what we have.
So see each one, see each one set upon or used or use its variable, but if C, H one is no use, then
there should be an error, you see.
So this is a bug.
It has to be a bug from the cube.
I d e okay, we can go to the debug for you or click over here.
So we can just otherwise see it, want to see it, too, to our live expression window.
Copy this and then I'll add it over here.
A copy this.
They're not allowed to see H2 over here like this.
So these are the current values.
So it's because it's run.
And this is the current state of it.
Right.
So we can get this exact same result that is stored in the two deery the array, because we we went
out of the debugging, came back, it sells, it says over here, failed to evaluate.
We can't remove this.
I'm going to stop it.
Remove it and add it to the.
We just confirmed that we have the same result.
I'm going to add our array here.
Okay, we are back with it.
And you can see the results is the same.
So if you have 10 of them, you can take them by the array indices one by one.
But normally, when using DNA, uh, DME, the advantage is so that you don't spend any process in cycles
having to read outside a buffer.
You can just rather than read the content of memory and store it in another variable, you can just
use sense of value index you to know that that is your channel one, your channel one.
So you wouldn't need to do this.
Right.
So it is.
If you have any questions regarding this, um, send me a message and I'll leave in the question and
answer this area and I'll see you later.
Have a nice day.